Guide to the Janice Rubin Papers, 1941-2015 MS 751
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Janice Rubin papers
1941-2015
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rubin, Janice
MS 751
1.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The collection consists of two boxes of correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, programs, photographic material, and media (VHS, audio cassettes, and cds) that document some of Janice Rubin's activities as a teacher, musician, and photographer within the Houston Jewish community from 1953 to 2015. Also included is a packet of materials provided to Jewish service members during World War II.
Biographical / Historical
Janice Rubin grew up in Fort Worth, Texas, and graduated from R.L. Paschal High School. She graduated from Rice University in 1976 and has been a Houston-based photographer since that time. She specializes in corporate and editorial photography. Known for creating warm, intimate portraits with strong emotional content, and graphic, poignant editorial shots, her clients include major corporations and institutions: ExxonMobil, The Ford Foundation, Allstate, The Houston Grand Opera, The Houston Symphony, Amnesty International, M.D. Anderson Cancer Center, and numerous others. Her work has appeared in publications in the United States and Europe including Smithsonian, Newsweek, Town and Country, Fortune, Rolling Stone, the New York Times, American Photographer, Esquire, Forbes, Geo, Harpers, L'Express, London Times, Ms. Magazine, Texas Monthly, and the Washington Post Magazine. Janice has exhibited internationally. She was the recipient of a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship for her participation in the travelling exhibit "The Ties that Bind: Photographers Look at The American Family." Her most widely seen touring exhibitions are "Survival of the Spirit: Jewish Lives in the Soviet Union," which toured 17 cities in the U.S. and Canada from 1987-1989, and "The Mikvah Project," which toured 34 cities in the U.S. and Europe from 2001-2015. Her work is included in the permanent collection of The Museum of Fine Arts, Houston. In addition to Rice, her photography archive is housed at the University of Houston Library, Special Collections.
She has been a member of the American Society of Media Photographers (ASMP) since 1986, and served as a board member of the Houston Center for Photography from 1988 through 1994. She served the City of Houston as a member of the Houston Municipal Arts Commission, 1986-1994, and Arts Task Force - Cultural Arts Council of Houston, 1991-1993, both Mayoral appointments.
In addition to photography, Janice serves as a hospital and hospice chaplain. Janice is also an educator, a lifelong musician, and recording artist.
Janice Rubin married artist Charles Wiese in Houston on 26 May 1991. Their son, Jacob, was born in 1995.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, photographs, slides, negatives, programs, news clippings, publicity material, VHS tapes, audio cassettes, compact discs, and a poster document some of Janice Rubin's activities as a teacher, musician, and photographer within the Houston Jewish community from 1953 to 2015. Of particular interest is the large amount of photographic material documenting a wide variety of people and activities including, a Brith Shalom student family history project, Jewish musicians and singers, and a rally in support of Soviet Jewry in Washington D.C. Also included is a packet of materials provided to Jewish service members during World War II.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in eight series as follows:
Series I: Correspondence; Series II: General; Series III: News Clippings; Series IV: Photographic Materials; Series V: Programs/Published Materials; Series VI: Publicity; Series VII: Media; Series VIII: Oversize
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The material was donated by Janice Rubin, April 2018 and May 2019
Index Terms
Subjects
Newspapers; World War (1939-1945)
Document Types
photographs; videotapes; audiotapes; slides (photographs); programs (documents); newsletters
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Brith Shalom. (Bellaire, Tex); Congregation Beth Yeshurun (Houston, Tex)
- Series I: Correspondence, ca. 1980's-2006
  - General correspondence, ca. 1980's (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Note from Rabbi Ranon Teller, 2006-05-23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: General, 1953-1999
  - Song Book - B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation, Texas A&M, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Congregation Brith Shalom (Bellaire) membership directory, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Congregation Brith Shalom Religious School teacher's agreement (Janice Rubin), 1994; 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III: News Clippings, 1984-2006
  - Newsweek - "Breakdancing at Beth Yeshurun Day School", 1984-07-02 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Houstonian Magazine - "Breakfast with Uncle Max", 1986-02 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Houston Post Magazine - "Janice Rubin in Russia", 1987-02-01 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - News clippings featuring Janice Rubin, 1995-2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jewish Spiritual Programming, 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Photographic Materials, 1980-1999
  - Seven Acres negatives, 1980-06 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dave and Beulah Yellen with Gigi Yellen photograph, Galveston, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Harold Farb photographs (1), contact sheet, and photographic negatives, 1984-01 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Slides from photos used in Newsweek article "Breakdancing at Beth Yeshurun Day School", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Seven Acres slides, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rubin, Propis, Resnick photograph, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kaplan family photographs (6), contact sheets (5), and negatives, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cantor David Propis photographs (4) and negatives, 1986-12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Washington D.C. rally slides, 1987-12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Judith Katzman (daughter) and Sylvia Levine photograph, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ira Black slides, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brith Shalom Cantor David Propis slides and negatives, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - U.O.S. Cantor Irving Dean slides, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hebrew Academy photographs (32), contact sheets (4), and negatives, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Kitzah Zayin photographs, Brith Shalom 9th grade Hebrew School, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series V: Programs/Published Materials, 1941-2000
  - Religious materials for Jewish service men (prayer book, Holy scriptures, National Jewish Welfare Board card, calendar, booklets), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Daroma U.S.Y. (United Synagogue Youth) Yearbook, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Event programs, 1978; 2011 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Concert programs, 1992-2015 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Tracing Family History" Kitah Zayin, 9th grade, Jewish Education News, vol. 20, no. 3, Fall/Winter 1999/2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Building for Our Future: New Campus Campaign 2000," The Hebrew Academy (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series VI: Publicity, 1982-2015
  - Publicity for upcoming Janice Rubin events, 1982-2015 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series VII: Media, 1986-2006
  - Cantor David Propis and congregation Brith Shalom Choir, "Shir Chadash b'Simchat Shabbat" [audio cassette], 1986-04-18 (Box 2)
  - Hazzan David Propis and the Brith Shalom Choir, "High Holiday Highlights" [audio cassette], 1992 (Box 2)
  - "A Decade of Song" - 10th Anniversary Concert honoring Cantor David Propis, Congregation Brith Shalom [VHS], 1993-05-23 (Box 2)
  - The Annual Brith Shalom Sisterhood Membership Event featuring Janice Rubin and Joy Rosenberg [VHS], 2004-10-11 (Box 2)
  - Cantor Steven Stoehr and the Brith Shalom Choir, Part 1 [CD], 2006-05-14 (Box 2)
  - Janice Rubin & Friends "Feels Like Family" Yiddish Folksongs [audio cassette] (Box 2)
  - Janice Rubin & Friends "Feels Like Family" Yiddish Folksongs [CD] (Box 2)
  - General, Sabbath, Siddur, and Seder Songs - Holiday Songs and Songs of Israel, "Shiru Besimcha - Sing with Joy," Cantor Irving Dean and Estelle Panzer [audio cassette] (Box 2)
  - Green Family Camp [audio cassette], n.d. (Box 2)
  - Freida Wiener - Yiddish audio cassette case, n.d. (Box 2)
- Series: VIII: Oversize, 1999-2005
  - Event poster - "Unmasking Judaism's Treasures: A Day of Exploration of the Soul," guests: Prager, Krassen, Zaslow, 2005-03-13 (Box 2)
  - 9th grade Kitah Zayin project photographs with stories (6), 1999-04 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series IX: Rice University Photographic Materials
  - Rice Design Alliance - Philip Johnson, Gerald Hines, and Karl Killian, 1981-02 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Phil Bedient, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dennis Huston, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Shepherd School of Music, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Susan Wood - Poet and Rice Professor, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minority Students in Engineering, 1997-03 (Box 2, Folder 7)